This video describes normal and abnormal fundal red reflex appearance.
A normal fundal red reflex examination is when there is no overall difference in the brightness and colour between the two eyes with the central corneal reflections.
Even a normal appearance of the fundal reflex will, however, vary depending on how far away you are and where the child is looking.
It is an active dynamic examination where you should move side to side and back and forth in and around arm's length from the patient.
Babies and children will also move their hands and eyes, making the reflex change the way it looks during the examination.
In a black baby, the reflex typically looks quite pale, with yellow and white and sometimes even blue as the main colour.
Importantly, in a normal examination, there should be no overall difference in the brightness and colour between the two eyes with the central corneal reflections.
An abnormal reflex is when there is a persistent, real difference in the brightness and colour between the two eyes.
A displaced corneal reflection, a dark patch present within the reflex of one eye or both eyes, or a completely absent red reflex.
An abnormal reflex test can indicate the presence of cataract, retinoblastoma, corneal scar, squint, refractive error or congenital problems such as coloboma.
These all require further assessment by a specialist.
Look at this reflex and ask yourself: is this normal or abnormal? The answers will follow afterwards.
You should now have a better understanding of what a normal reflex looks like, as well as abnormal reflexes, and be able to suggest the most likely cause.